A Guide to the Loudoun County Virginia Military Separation Notices, 1918-1995
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Loudoun County Virginia Military Separation Notices 1918-1995
Thomas Balch Library
M 004
3 manuscript boxes (1.3 cu ft; 2,136 items)
This collection represents induction and discharge records photocopied by William Loy, Deputy Clerk, from Loudoun County court books. The collection includes separation notices for men and women and all races, but may not include every Loudoun County resident who served in the military.
William Loy
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restricted collection.
Since access to the records by general public is restricted to 72 years after a record was created researchers seeking to access this information must do so through a database index listing the name of the soldier, and as available: date of induction, branch of service, birthplace and date of separation. Virginia military separation notices contain privacy protected information such as social security numbers and medical information. For records created 72 years or less access is limited to the following: the subject of the record (the veteran); the duly qualified conservator or guardian of the subject of the record; the next-of-kin, if the veteran is deceased (The next of kin may be the following: surviving spouse that has not remarried; father, mother, son, daughter, sister, or brother); the duly qualified executor or administrator of the estate of the subject of the record; an attorney, attorney-in-fact, or other agent or representative of any of the persons described above, acting pursuant to a written power-of-attorney or other written authorization; or a duly authorized representative of an agency or instrumentality of federal, state, or local government seeking the record in the ordinary course of performing its official duties. Requests must be in writing on Military Separation Notices filed in the folder: Loudoun County Virginia Request Form.
Acquisition Information
Loudoun County Courthouse, Leesburg, VA, 1995
Alternative Form Available
Original copies of records may be on file at the Loudoun County Courthouse.
Accruals
1995.0001
Historical Information
Military induction and discharge records were frequently filed in a courthouse by military personal in the locale of induction and/or discharge to provide legal verification of military service.
Scope and Content
This collection represents induction and discharge records photocopied by William Loy, Deputy Clerk, from Loudoun County court books. These records were given to Thomas Balch Library in 1995 for researcher use. Subsequent federal rulings concerning privacy require these records to be restricted for 72 years from date of creation. Access to this collection is through a database index listing the name of the soldier, and as available: date of induction, branch of service, birthplace and date of separation.
The collection includes separation notices for men and women and all races, but may not include every Loudoun County resident who served in the military. Separation notices, representing all branches of military service, include information on the date and place of birth, physical description, race, marital status and civilian occupation of the soldier. Also included is rank, military organization, date of induction or enlistment, place of entry into service, military occupation, battles and campaigns, decorations and citations, wounds received in action, service outside the continental United States, prior service, total length of service and reasons for separation. Naval records also list training schools attended and places of service (ships and naval stations). In addition to the separation notices, many army records also contain a separation qualification record documenting the soldier's military and civilian education and occupations. This document may also include the soldier's social security number.
Due to the nature of photocopying some records in this collection are difficult to read.
Arrangement
Documents are arranged alphabetically within each year in two groups: separation notices and separation notices with only induction information completed. Separation notices in this collection cover the years 1918-1919, 1921 and 1941-1995. Separation notice forms with only induction information completed are filed at the end of the collection (Box 3, Folder 25) and cover the years 1941-1943 and 1945.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Location of Originals
Original copies of records may be on file at the Loudoun County Courthouse.
Other Finding Aid
Military Records Database Index
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
See Vertical file under WWII
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - 1918 (7)
  - 1919 (13)
  - 1921 (1)
  - 1941 (1)
  - 1942 (3)
  - 1943 (18)
  - 1944 (39)
  - 1945 A-C (126)
  - 1945 D-H (124)
  - 1945 J-P (137)
  - 1945 R-Y (155)
  - 1946 A-C (92)
  - 1946 D-H (105)
- (Box 2)
  - 1946 J-P (121)
  - 1946 R-W (146)
  - 1947 (53)
  - 1948 (11)
  - 1949 (6)
  - 1950 (2)
  - 1951 (1)
  - 1952 (8)
  - 1953 (5)
  - 1954 (13)
  - 1955 (6)
  - 1956 (11)
  - 1957 (7)
  - 1958 (9)
  - 1959 (4)
  - 1960 (7)
  - 1961 (5)
  - 1962 (7)
  - 1963 (5)
  - 1964 (11)
  - 1965 (16)
  - 1966 (10)
  - 1967 (23)
  - 1968 (54)
  - 1969 (36)
  - 1970 (63)
  - 1971 (57)
- (Box 3)
  - 1972 (39)
  - 1973 (28)
  - 1974 (14)
  - 1975 (29)
  - 1976 (11)
  - 1977 (19)
  - 1978 (11)
  - 1979 (37)
  - 1980 (20)
  - 1981 (16)
  - 1982 (19)
  - 1983 (14)
  - 1984 (11)
  - 1985 (11)
  - 1986 (19)
  - 1987 (21)
  - 1988 (19)
  - 1989 (29)
  - 1990 (26)
  - 1991 (44)
  - 1992 (33)
  - 1993 (15)
  - 1994 (26)
  - 1995 (13 items)
  - Induction Records 1941-1943, 1945, n.d. (95)